Guide to the Cornish, Winstanley, and Tower Records 1889-1896
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Cornish, Winstanley, and Tower Records
1889-1896
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 076
Cornish, Winstanley, and Tower
1 linear foot 2 boxes
Cornish, Winstanley, and Tower was a Missoula, Montana, law firm. The collection consists of outgoing correspondence and financial records from the law firm.
Historical Note
The law firm of Cornish, Winstanley, and Tower began in April 1889 in Missoula, Montana, as Fairchild and Cornish. It was founded by J.H. Fairchild, who came to western Montana in 1866 to explore the possibility of operating a steamboat between Lake Pend Oreille and the Jocko River. He left Montana to several years and returned to Missoula in September, 1888. The other founding partner was John Cornish, who came to Missoula in 1886 or 1887. In January 1890, the firm became Fairchild, Cornish & Company when J.A. Armitage and E.A Winstanley joined the firm. Armitage came to Missoula in 1889 from Helena, Montana, where he had been with a real estate firm. Winstanley came to Helena as Land Agent for the Northern Pacific Railway in 1883. In 1885, he moved to Missoula, where he employed by the Big Blackfoot Milling Company. In Febuary 1891, the firm became Cornish, Winstanley, and Tower when E.H. Tower joined the firm. He had come to Missoula in summer of 1890 when he briefly joined M.E. Rutherford in a mining-real estate business.
The firm dealt mostly in real estate and land improvement.
The collection consists of outgoing correspondence and financial records from the law firm. Correspondence is mostly with other attorneys in and outside Missoula on real estate dealings. Financial records document general finances of the firm, and also contain two volumes of property for sale in and around Missoula.
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Correspondence, 2 volumes, 1889-1891
Series II: Financial Records, 8 volumes, 1889-1896
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The collection was originally given to the Missoula Public Library, along with materials that have been processed as Mss 379, Mss 380, and Mss 381.
Transferred to the Archives from the Missoula Public Library, 1978.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Fairchild and Cornish (Missoula, Mont.); Fairchild, Cornish & Company (Missoula, Mont.)
Law firms--Montana -- Missoula; Practice of law--Montana --Missoula; Real estate development -- Montana--Missoula; Real property--Montana -- Missoula
Business records -- Montana--Missoula
Montana; Labor History
Real estate lawyers -- Montana--Missoula
- Correspondence, 1889-1891; Series I; 2 volumes
  This series contains outgoing correspondence in letterpress books. The correspondence, arranged chronologically, ranges from mundane exchanges with office suppliers, to more substantive correspondence on behalf of clients. Exchanges are mostly with other attorneys in and out of Montana.
  - 1889-1890 (Box-volume 1/1)
  - March-September, 1891 (Box-volume 1/2)
- Financial Records, 1889-1896; Series II; 8 volumes
  This series contains financial records from the law firm. Most concern the day to day business of collecting fees and dispersing them to the partners. Many of the records show an active continuing interest in Missoula real estate, particularly south of the Clark Fork River, and dealings with the South Missoula Land Company. Two volumes of records of property for sale list sales in and outside Missoula, giving quite detailed descriptions of land, timber, and other factors, and indicate dealings with and for Hiram Knowles and the Missoula Land Improvement Company.
  - General journal, 1889-1890 (Box-volume 1/3)
  - General ledger, 1892 (Box-volume 1/4)
  - Cash book, 1889-1891 (Box-volume 1/5)
  - Cash book, 1891-1896 (Box-volume 2/6)
  - Record of property for sale, undated (Box-volume 2/7)
  - Record of property for sale, undated (Box-volume 2/8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1890 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - General ledger, 1889-1890 (Box-volume 2/10)